Guide to the Robert Mearns Yerkes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Personal Papers, 1822-1965; Series VI; 21.5 linear feet (35 boxes)
  - Family: Relatives
    - Watterson, Carrie Norton, 1903-1923, undated (Box 166, Folder 2617)
    - Yerkes, Helen K., 1898-1944 (Box 166, Folder 261819)
    - Yerkes, Mabel, 1880-1883 (Box 167, Folder 2620)
    - Yerkes, Miles C. and family, 1900-1953 (Box 167, Folder 2621-2623)
    - Yerkes, David Mercer, 1944-1946 (Box 167, Folder 2624)
    - Yerkes, Eleanor, 1939-1944 (Box 167, Folder 2625)
    - Yerkes, Myles C., Jr., 1936-1956 (Box 167, Folder 2626)
    - Yerkes "round robin" letters, 1926-1963 (Box 167, Folder 2627-2630)
    - Bound copy of letters to Robert M. Yerkes from parents and two younger brothers, 1894-1905 (Box 167, Folder 2631)
    - Yerkes, Silas Marshall, 1894-1924 (Box 167, Folder 2632)
    - Yerkes, Susanna Addis Carrell, 1899-1905 (Box 167, Folder 2633-2636)
    - Yerkes, Susanna Addis Carrell, 1906-1913 (Box 168, Folder 2637)
    - Yerkes, William Augustus, 1899-1956 (Box 168, Folder 2638-1943)
    - Yerkes, other, 1900-1956 (Box 168, Folder 2644)
  - Diaries: Robert M. Yerkes
    - Books read at West Chester and Collegeville, 1891-1893 (Box 169, Folder 2645)
    - Books read at Collegeville, 1891-1893 (Box 169, Folder 2646)
    - Daily Journal, 1893 (Box 169, Folder 2647)
    - Daily record, 1894 (Box 169, Folder 2648)
    - Third year at Ursinus, 1895 (Box 169, Folder 2649)
    - Daily record, junior-senior year at Ursinus, 1896 (Box 169, Folder 2650)
    - Senior year at Ursinus, 1897 (Box 169, Folder 2651)
    - Daily Journal at Harvard University, 1898 (Box 169, Folder 2652)
    - Harvard Graduate School, 1899-1901 (Box 170, Folder 2653-2655)
    - Harvard University, 1902 (Box 170, Folder 2656)
    - Diary, 1903-1904 (Box 170, Folder 2657-2658)
    - Diary, 1905-1913 (Box 171, Folder 2659-2662)
    - War journal, 1917-1918 (Box 171, Folder 2663)
    - Diary, 1919-1920 (Box 172, Folder 2664-2665)
    - Record of anthropoid work in Havana, Cuba, 1924 (Box 172, Folder 2666)
    - Log and notes of European and African Journey, 1929 (Box 172, Folder 2667)
    - Typescript of African part of journey, made in 1977, 1929 (Box 172, Folder 2668)
    - Diary, 1940 (Box 172, Folder 2669)
    - Diary, 1941-1943 (Box 173, Folder 2670-2672)
    - Memo of war emergency and professional consultations, 1943-1945 (Box 173, Folder 2673)
    - Diary, 1944-1947 (Box 174, Folder 2674-2677)
    - Diary, 1948-1951 (Box 175, Folder 2678-2681)
    - Diary, 1952-1954 (Box 176, Folder 2682-2684)
    - Transcriptions of passages from 1893, 1897, 1902, and 1903 diaries, 1893-1903 (Box 176, Folder 2685)
  - Diaries: Ada Watterson Yerkes
    - Summer of 1902 in Europe (Box 176, Folder 2686)
    - Diaries, 1929, 1934 (Box 176, Folder 2687)
    - Diaries, 1939-1963 (Box 177, Folder 2688)
    - Date book, 1936-1952 (Box 177, Folder 2689)
    - Household accounts, 1905-1912 (Box 177, Folder 2690)
  - Oversize
    Transferred to CF86
    - Sound recording of baby gorilla vocalization, 1950 (Box 178, Folder 2691)
    - Yerkes - E.B. Titchener correspondence at Cornell University, 1907-1908 (Box 178, Folder 2692)
    - Trunk of psychological testing materials, 1917-1918 (Box 179)
    - Charts on psychological testing, 1917-1918 (Box 184)
- 1985 Yerkes Addition, 1925-1985; 1.0 linear feet (3 boxes)
  The YERKES ADDITION was donated to Yale University Library by Roberta Yerkes Blanshard in May 1985. It consists of three boxes of correspondence and other material of Roberta Yerkes Blanshard, concerning Robert M. Yerkes and the Yerkes Regional Primate Research Center at Emory University in Atlanta, Georgia. The papers are divided into four series and the material spans the dates 1925-1985.
  Series I, PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE, has twelve folders of correspondence covering the period 1965-1985. Among the major subjects discussed are the saving of mountain gorillas, pygmy chimpanzees, the importance of Yerkes' primate research, publications concerning Yerkes, and the 1976 Yerkes Centennial Conference.
  SUBJECT FILES are found in boxes 181-182, folders 13-44, of the YERKES ADDITION. They contain material on the disposal of Yerkes' books, periodicals, and office furniture, requests for information, and correspondence concerning the gold medal awarded Yerkes in 1954 by the New York Zoological Society. Also included is correspondence concerning reprints of The Mental Life of Monkeys and Apes, Yerkes' first major publication on primates, and The Great Apes. These files also contain comments on the work of those writing on Yerkes. Folder 26 has minutes of meetings of The Board of Scientific Directors for the Yerkes Laboratories. The meeting for October 1963 includes a eulogy for Ada Watterson Yerkes. Folders 29-44 contain material on the Yerkes Regional Primate Research Center. The files contain correspondence with officers and employees of the Center, information on the dedication of the Yerkes Center on October 28, 1965 and the 1976 Yerkes Centennial Conference, a list of publications, and an incomplete run of the Yerkes Newsletter.
  Series IV, WRITINGS, has copies of Progress in Ape Research, which is the published proceedings of the Yerkes Centennial Conference; The Mental Life of Monkeys and Apes; and The Pygmy Chimpanzee. Progress in Ape Research contains an informative section on "Historical Beginnings of Research on Great Apes." The ADDITION concludes with two folders of biographical material.
  The YERKES ADDITION fills boxes 181-183 of the Robert M. Yerkes Papers. It contains material from four series, Series I, PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Series II, SUBJECT FILES, is arranged alphabetically by broad subject area. The material is Series IV, WRITINGS, is in chronological order, while the PERSONAL PAPERS are in alphabetical order.
  - Professional Correspondence
    - Bourne, Geoffrey H.
      See: box 181, folder 29, Bourne, Geoffrey H.
    - Coolidge, Harold J., Jr., 1982-1985 (Box 181, Folder 1)
    - Crawford, Meredith P.
      See: box 181, folder 9
    - Elder, James H., 1976-1977 (Box 181, Folder 2)
    - Fossey, Dian
      See: box 181, folder 6
    - Goodall, Jane Van Lawick, 1972-1978 (Box 181, Folder 3)
    - Gould, Stephen Jay, 1983, 1985 (Box 181, Folder 4)
    - Haslerud, George M.
      See: box 181, folders 22-23
    - Kinder, Elaine F., 1965 (Box 181, Folder 5)
    - McIlvaine, Alice N, 1973, 1979, undated (Box 181, Folder 6)
    - McIlvaine, Robinson, 1973, 1979, undated (Box 181, Folder 6)
    - Marshall, Louise H., 1981 (Box 181, Folder 7)
    - Miles, Walter R., 1965 (Box 181, Folder 8)
    - Morford, Helen S., 1984 (Box 181, Folder 9)
    - Riesen, Austin H.
      See: box 181, folder 23
    - Riopelle, Arthur J.
      See: box 181, folder 32
    - Roberts, Helen, 1985 (Box 181, Folder 10)
    - Sears, Robert R., 1981 (Box 181, Folder 11)
    - Seyfarth, Robert M., 1982 (Box 181, Folder 12)
    - Townsend, Murray
      See: box 181, folder 33
  - Subject Files
    - Miscellaneous
      - Disposal of books, 1951-1978, undated (Box 181, Folder 13)
      - Disposal of non-book items, 1967-1972 (Box 181, Folder 14)
      - Disposal of office furniture, etc., 1952-1955 (Box 181, Folder 15)
      - Disposal of office journals, books, and reprints, 1944-1959 (Box 181, Folder 16-18)
      - Requests for information, 1964-1980, undated (Box 181, Folder 19)
      - Sale of periodicals, 1925-1944 (Box 181, Folder 20)
    - Organizations
      - New York Zoological Society, 1954-1985 (Box 181, Folder 21)
    - Works by Yerkes
      - Reprint of The Mental Life of Monkeys and Apes (1916), 1978-1983 (Box 181, Folder 22-23)
      - Reprint of The Great Apes (1929), 1966-1971 (Box 181, Folder 24)
    - Yale University
      - Institute of Psychology: Manson barn, 1985 (Box 181, Folder 25)
    - Yerkes Laboratories of Primate Biology
      - Board of Scientific Directors, 1962-1963 (Box 181, Folder 26)
      - Clippings, etc., 1956-1963 (Box 181, Folder 27)
      - Orange Park, Florida, 1972, 1980 (Box 181, Folder 28)
    - Yerkes Regional Primate Research Center
      - Bourne, Geoffrey H., 1971-1984 (Box 181, Folder 29)
      - Fitz-Gerald, Frances L., 1964-1985 (Box 181, Folder 30)
      - Johns, Nellie, 1968 (Box 181, Folder 31)
      - Riopelle, Arthur J., 1978 (Box 181, Folder 32)
      - Townsend, Murray, 1965-1978 (Box 181, Folder 33)
      - Dedication, 1965 (Box 181, Folder 34)
      - Robert M. Yerkes Centennial Conference, 1976 (Box 181, Folder 35)
      - Printed material, 1968-1973 (Box 181, Folder 36)
      - Publications, list of, 1962-1976 (Box 182, Folder 37)
      - Yerkes Newsletter, 1964-1978 (Box 182, Folder 38-44)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - Progress in Ape Research, ed. by Geoffrey H. Bourne, 1977 (Box 182, Folder 45)
      - The Mental Life of Monkeys and Apes, reprint with introduction by George M. Haslerud, 1979 (Box 182, Folder 46)
      - The Pygmy Chimpanzee: Evolutionary Biology and Behavior, ed. by Randall L. Susman, 1984 (Box 183, Folder 47)
  - Personal Papers
    - Biographical
      - Material re Bucks County Boyhood, 1984-1985 (Box 183, Folder 48)
      - "Terman and Yerkes once compared notes on Orwell," by Carl Degler, 1984 (Box 183, Folder 49)
- Additional Material, 1929-1983; Accession 1989-M-031; 1.5; (1 box)
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1989 February
  Received from: Roberta Y. Blanshard, 1988 Dec 8, 1993 Jun
  - Guest book pages from Pleasant Hill Farm, Franklin, New Hampshire, 1912-1983 May (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Pencil drawing done in Conakry, Guinea by Roberta Yerkes, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Roberta Yerkes from her father, 1942 December 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Critique of Pure Reason by Immanuel Kant, given to Roberta Yerkes by her father (1942), 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Army Letters, 1861-1865, inscribed by author, Oliver Willcox Norton, gift to Robert Yerkes, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Additional Material, 1921-1924; Accession 1989-M-076; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1989 Apr
  Received from: David Yerkes, 1989 Mar 23
  - Correspondence
    - Gould, Charles W., 1921 August 25-December 12, 1922 January 23-December 21, 1923 February 3-December 27, 1924 February 14-August 2 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Additional Material, 1863-1992; Accession 1993-M-073; 2.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Addition Inventory by Diane E. Kaplan 1993 Jun
  Received from: Roberta Yerkes Blanshard, 1993 May 27
  - Inventory of and notes on addition by Roberta Yerkes Blanshard, Circa 1992 (Box 1)
  - Norton-Watterson family papers, 1863-1920 (Box 1)
  - Ada Watterson Yerkes papers, 1874-1905, 1904-1906 (Box 1)
  - Ada Watterson Yerkes Correspondence, 1915, 1920s, 1930-1935 (Box 1)
  - Ada Watterson Yerkes correspondence, 1936-1957 (Box 2)
  - Ada Watterson Yerkes papers re family matters, 1904-1963 (Box 2)
  - David Norton Yerkes papers, 1920-1992 (Box 2)